So we introduced action creators in the last lectures and you learned that they are especially useful when
Bylece, son derslerde eylem yaratclar tantld ve asenkron kod ile alrken zellikle
working with asynchronous code
yararl olduklarn rendiniz.
because together with redux-thunk, that middleware, we could basically find a place to execute our asynchronous
nk bu middleware redux phunk ile birlikte, temelde bir eylem gnderirken asenkron kodumuzu altrmak
code when dispatching an action and block that original dispatching to then just dispatch another action,
iin bir yer bulabiliriz ve bu orijinal sevkyat engellemek iin sadece o tarafndan ele alnan baka
all that handled by that
bir eylem gndeririz.
redux-thunk middleware
Redux phunk katman yazlm.
once our asynchronous task is done. Now with that, we got this new actions file which not only holds our
Ezamansz grevi imdi bununla bittiinde, yalnzca eylem trlerimizi tutmakla kalmayan bu yeni eylemleri
action types,
de sonlandrdk.
so the unique identifiers
Yani benzersiz tanmlayclar.
so to say
Demek ki.
but also all these creator functions which use these identifiers. Obviously our file here in the demo
Ancak bu tanmlayclar kullanan tm bu yaratc ilevler akas demo projemize den
project isn't that big,
bu kadar byk deil.
we can of course simply stick to one file but we also split up the reducers into counter and result
Elbette bir dosyaya yaptrabiliriz ancak ayn zamanda reticileri kart sonuta ikiye blyoruz ve
and you typically also do that for actions as your application grows and you're going to see that
bunu uygulamanz bydke siz de bunu eylemler iin yapyorsunuz ve bunu greceksiniz.
in the burger builder project. Therefore I'll create new files here, I'll create a counter.js file
Ve Bergere Boulder projesi bu nedenle burada yeni dmeler yaratyor; burada bir kar jr'n hatas
and I'll create a result.js file,
yaratp decek bir sonu yaratacam.
so just like in the reducers folder, now for actions. I'll rename the actions file to action types
Dolaysyla, imdi eylemlerin yeniden adlandrld redktrler klasrnde olduu gibi, eylemler eylem trlerine der.
because here, I now only want to export these unique identifiers, so that
nk imdi sadece bu benzersiz tanmlaycy vermek istiyorum l ld.
I have one file providing all the action types my application knows and theoretically, you could of course
Uygulamamn bildii tm eylem trlerini salayan bir dosyam var ve teorik olarak
also split up into multiple files.
elbette birden ok dosyaya blnebilirsin.
Now I'll take my action creators and put them into their respective files
imdi, ection yaratclarm alp ilgili dosyalarna koyacam.
so for the counter, I'll take the increment, decrement, add and subtract action creator, cut it from
Bu yzden saya iin, krom art ve aksiyon tr dosyasndan oluturulan ection yaratcs
the action types file and put it into the counter file.
ekleme ve karma ilemini alp saya dne koyacam.
Now of course, this reference to this constant won't work anymore because that constant now lives in
yaplan bu referans artk almayacak, nk bu sabit imdi farkl bir dosyada yayor.
a different file.
Elbette bu sabite
So I should import that and I will import everything as action types from ./actionTypes which
Bu yzden bunu almalym ve eylem trlerine erimek iin nokta biimlendirme eylem trlerinden eylem trleri olarak her eyi ie
allows me to now set up my types by accessing action types and then the constants which we do export
aktaracam; bu da eylem trne ve ardndan o dosyada verdiim sabitlerden erierek benim tr ayarlamama
in that file.
izin veriyor.
I'll do the same for decrement and of course also for add and subtract, like this,
Ayn eyi Decora insanl iin de yapacam ve elbette ayrca eklemek ve kartmak iin de aynsn yapacam.
finally also for subtract.
Son olarak da karma iin.
So that's the updated counter.js file with the action creators for the counter related actions,
te bu yzden, bir kar J eylemcilerle saya ile ilgili eylemler iin den J.
of course I'll do the same for the result, take my saveResult, storeResult and this deleteResult
iin de ayn eyi yapacam tazmene saldr salam bir maaza saldrs ve sadece Rosol yaratcs silin.
creator,
Tabii ki saldr
so that also includes the asynchronous one
Bylece asenkron da bulunur.
and then I'll also import everything as action types from this action types file
Ardndan da, her eylem trn bu eylem trlerinden alana kadar her eyi ie aktarn.
and with that, we can also use the action types we import to assign the right types here.
Ayrca, burada doru trlere atamak iin aldmz eylem trlerini kullanabilirsiniz.
So storeResult, in storeResult itself I just have my asynchronous code dispatching saveResult
Dolaysyla salt depolamak depolanr kendisini zmek iin neden sadece senkronize olmayan kod gnderme sonunda
in the end and then deleteResult, I of course also want to dispatch deleteResult.
Savir saldrs ve sonra da drizzles silmek da silme sonucu gndermek istiyoruz.
So now I got my action creators outsourced, the action types file now only contains my action types and
imdi, gerek yaratclarmn eylem trleri dosyasn yalnzca hareket trlerini ierdiinden ve bunlar da aktardracamdan
exports them,
emin oldum.
now I also want to have one file exporting all my action creators,
imdi de tm ection yaratclarm da aktaran bir dosya istiyorum.
so I'll create an index.js file here and in there, I'll actually use a syntax you might have not
Yani tm bu doru indeks nokta J. S. burada der ve aslnda daha nce grmediin
seen before,
bir szdizimi kullanrsn.
I'll just export something from a file.
Bir dosyadan bir eyler ihra edeceim.
I can do that so I don't even import it in this file,
Bunu yapabilirim, bu yzden bu sonbaharda ithal etmem.
I just have one file, the index.js file
Bir sonraki Cheras'n dmesi iin bir tane d var.
which groups
Hangi gruplar.
all exports from separate files, so that in the end I can always point to that file to import something
saya JS hatasndan bir ey da aktaralm ve bir eyin gerekten bir her eyin listesi.
from any of the files I'll point to in that file here. So let me quickly do that, let's export something from the
Ayr dosyalardaki tm ihracat bylece sonunda her eyden nce herhangi bir dosyadan bir eyler ie aktarmak veya
counter.js file and that something actually will be a list of everything
bu dosyaya iaret etmek iin kme iaret edebilir; bu sayede,
this file does offer, like add, subtract, increment and decrement.
Bu dosya, karm ve zarar azaltmak gibi bir teklif sunar.
And this really is just an advanced feature if someone wants to use such a set up of the project to handle
Ve bu gerekten de sadece gelimi bir zelliktir zirveler, elbette birok eylem ve eylem yaratcs ile daha byk
a bigger project with lots and lots of actions and action creators of course,
bir projeyi ele almak iin byle bir proje seti kullanmak istiyor.
it's overkill for this demo project but it will make more sense later when we reach our burger builder
Bu demo projesi iin fazlasyla ac ekiyor ancak daha sonra Bergere Buller'imize ulatmzda daha mantkl olacak ve
and I want to teach you the concept right now already.
u anda konsepti size retmek istiyorum.
So I'll also export something from the result file here that will be storeResult and it will be deleteResult,
ancak tabii ki ihra edilebilir, ancak hibir Rafal'a asla ihtiya duymayacam. benim grubumun iine.
saveResult is not exported here though I could of course also export it but I'll never need it
Dolaysyla, sonu dosyasndaki tm ihracat sonular buradan saklanacak ve deleter saldr
in any other file so I won't include it into my grouping.
olacaktr Saldr saldrs burada ihra edilemez,
Now what this allows me to do is to later just import from index.js and actually import from any of
imdi yapmam salayan ey daha sonra sadece dizin JS'den ie aktarmak ve aslnda bu dizindeki
these two files which I group in this index.js file.
Jaspal grubundaki bu iki dosyann herhangi birinden ie aktarmaktr.
Now that's just a tiny improvement to make our files even a bit leaner, now what I also need to do is I need
imdi dosyalarmz biraz daha yasz hale getirmek iin ufak bir ilerleme var, imdi yapmam
to adjust my reducer file where I do import these action types, so in counter.js where I import action
gerekeni redktr dosyam ayarlamamz lazmdr burada diese eylem trlerini ie aktaracaz, bu nedenle imdi
types, that now lives in the actionTypes.js file in the actions folder, the same adjustment needs
eylem trlerinde yaayan ection trlerini nereden alacam J'yi ayn ayarlamann yaplmasna ihtiya duyulan eylemler klasrne dtnde balatn
to be made in the result reducer,
ve sonu azaltc.
there I also now import from the action types file in the actions folder. And finally in the counter
Burada eylem klasrndeki eylem trleri dosyasndan da ie aktarabilirim ve nihayet burada
where I dispatch, here I refer to action creators and that now actually should point to the index.js
gnderdiim sayata eylem yaratclarna atfta bulundum ve aslnda hibir ey dizin JS hatasna iaret
file,
etmemeliydi.
so /index. Let's quickly restart npm start to see if it really has problems or just is stuck in
Bu yzden eik izgi indeksi Hemen yeniden balayalm ve gerekten sorun olup olmadn veya yeniden ina srecinde skm olup
the rebuild process,
olmadn grmek iin balayalm.
we do find an issue in the counter.js file,
Saya JS hatasnda bir sorun buluyoruz.
it doesn't like my imports here, action types,
e aktarmm senin hareket trlerinden holanmaz.
oh because I mistyped here it's actions,
Oh, nk burada yanl yaptm, eylemler.
that's a typo in the file name, the file name should be action types.
Bu, dosya adnda bir yazm hatas olup, dosya ad eylem trleri olmaldr.
Now with the file name changed, I need to change all my imports in the other action files too,
imdi dosya ad deitiyse ortalama eylemdeki tm ithalatlarm deitirmem gerekiyor.
there I was referencing the wrong file, with all that adjusted to really point to actiontypes.js,
Gerekten harekete geirici eyler iaret etmek iin ayarlanm olan tmyle yanl dosyaya bavuruyordu.
we should have a working application again just as before with asynchronous storage available.
Asenkron saklama zellii ile daha nce olduu gibi yine bir alma bavurusu yapmamz gerektii iin.
Now however with a bit more split up action creators over multiple files, as I said for this demo project
Ancak, bu demo projesinin ar derecede kabiliyeti iin sylediim gibi, imdi birden fazla dosyaya kar eylem yaratclarn biraz
overkill but definitely something you should keep in mind for bigger projects because what it allows
daha blnmken, daha byk projeler iin aklnzda bulundurmanz gereken bir ey var; nk
you is that you have files with only a few action creators in each file which makes it easier to find
size izin verdiklerine gre, her birinde yalnzca birka ection yaratcs olan dosyalarnz var dosyasn deitirmenizi veya
that action creator you want it to change or check.
kontrol etmenizi istediiniz l eylem yaratcs bulmanz kolaylatrr.
So this is why I chose that setup and it is something I wanted to show you for your bigger projects.
te bu yzden bu kurulumu setim ve daha byk projeleriniz iin gstermek istediim bir ey.